Guide to the Nancy Dawson and Herman Wouk Collection
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Nancy Dawson and Herman Wouk Collection,
1952-1965.
Dawson, Nancy, 1920-
0.42 linear ft (1 document box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0331
4078684
This collection contains primarily correspondence between author Herman Wouk and his secretary and research assistant, Nancy Dawson.
Historical Note
Nancy Dawson (neé Nancy Scott Causey) was born on May 17th 1920 in Greensboro, North Carolina. She attended the School of General Studies from 1949 to 1951 and received a B.S. in English on October 31st 1951. A few years later she began working for writer Herman Wouk. Wouk was living in the Virgin Islands with his wife Betty Sarah and their two children, Abraham and Joseph. Since Wouk was an extremely private person, he wanted few people to be able to reach him. Dawson was his point person in the United States and was often called upon to run important errands and conduct business for him. As Wouk's research assistant, Dawson sent along bibliographies, research notes, and citations for relevant texts. She also handled all of his incoming mail. Any interesting letters were passed onto Wouk, but the bulk of the letters consisted of Dawson summarizing that week's mail.
Scope and Content
The Nancy Dawson and Herman Wouk Collection is composed primarily of correspondence between Wouk and Dawson over a nine year span. There is also a small amount of subject files related to Wouk as a writer and to specific works of his.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1956-1965
Series II: Subject Files, 1952-1960
Subjects
Wouk, Herman, 1915-; Columbia College (New York, N.Y.)--Students.; Authors, American.; American literature--20th century.; Biographical sketches.; Correspondence.; Research Notes.; Virgin Islands.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
Researchers must acquire written permission from Mrs. Ralph Burk Dawson in order to access the collection.
Gift of Mrs Ra]ph B. Dawson, 1968.
Selected Material at Columbia
Herman Wouk Papers
- Series I: Correspondence, 1956-1965
  Series I contains letters sent between Nancy Dawson and Herman Wouk. Topics discussed included researching needs, family life (both Dawson and Wouk), current affairs, the field of publishing, and writing.
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1961-1962 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1962 July-1963 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1964-1965 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1952-1960
  This small series holds several files including biographical sketches about Herman Wouk used for publicity purposed, articles about his books, research notes for Youngblood Hawke, and several miscellaneous items.
  - Biographical Material on Wouk, 1953- 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Research Notes, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)